<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Blog by Vishal Naik]]></title><description><![CDATA[Blog by Vishal Naik]]></description><link>http://github.com/dylang/node-rss</link><generator>GatsbyJS</generator><lastBuildDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 09:09:29 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[Building Software in the Age of AI]]></title><description><![CDATA[What does AI leave for the vaunted software engineers who are staring at AI disrupting their own jobs?]]></description><link>https://vishalnaik.org/posts/building-software-ai-age</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://vishalnaik.org/posts/building-software-ai-age</guid><pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 14:25:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Up until a couple years back, software engineering was one of the most vaunted jobs. It became even more so during the covid bubble on the back of a digital and SaaS boom.
Salaries of even entry to mid level engineers skyrocketed during those days and demanding multiples of salaries just a couple years back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI has indisputably burst that bubble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all, no one predicted that coding, thought of as a highly analytical, deep thinking activity would be one of the first jobs to get disrupted by LLMs.
In hindsight of course, it makes sense that coding agents using LLMs would be great at coding: huge training data corpus. Programming languages impose syntax, there are tons of coding examples to learn from, LLMs learn the syntax and are able to apply an solution to a given context very well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So well that now you can build software by just talking to AI without even having any programming experience. The era of “vibe coding” is upon us - it’s just unevenly distributed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And as has been claimed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The “de-nerdification of programming is now complete  - &lt;a href=&quot;https://vivekhaldar.com/articles/the-de-nerdification-of-programming/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the nerd has a nostalgic feeling of loss at this impressive achievement. Someone called this feeling vesperance: “the solitary emotion of wistful recognition of the present as a fading era, tinged with anticipation for an unrecognizable, transformative future.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As many, I was caught up in this feeling of “vesperence” for a while too. When you initially start using AI, it can be a sinking feeling to see how AI is able to zero-shot working solutions, debug using intricate implementation details you learnt the hard way etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LLMs immediately depreciate previously thought of as like intricate programming language syntax, knowledge of APIs, navigating a vast code base besides the coding itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as you use more, you realise, it is a tool to lean in to. And once you do that more, you begin to enjoy using it to a point you don’t want to write software without it. The more you use it you also become curious about how it works and start learning about Transformer, study the Build an LLM book, work through nano GPT etc. You also read the “Evolution of intelligence” book and marvel about how intelligence evolved in living beings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then you know it’s not something to be feared and just a tool. At least, not yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You also realise how it is not a silver bullet for software development either.
Jagged intelligence, catastrophic forgetting, lack of continuous learning and zero agency are serious gaps that mean that AI doesn’t replace a software engineer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the nature of the job has changed. AI certainly eats a lot of tasks that a programmer has to do. But that yields the human more time to work on higher leverage things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, where does that leave the software engineer? What skill will become more important?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But before that, how is AI most effective now:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;ai-as-a-pair-programmer&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ai-as-a-pair-programmer&quot; aria-label=&quot;ai as a pair programmer permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;AI as a pair programmer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With AI coding agents like Claude Code, Codex etc taking much of the heavy lifting of writing the code with delightful developer experience, the job of the engineer shifts to becoming a navigator in a pair programming set up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typically, a “pair programming” set up involves a driver who has the control of keyboard and the mouse. The driver implements the coding requirement, fixes compiler errors, refactors etc  and the navigator guides, thinks about bigger picture, abstractions, design, non-functional requirements, how the solution fits into the context etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With coding agents, the developer role shifts to navigating or steering the AI to a desired solution while using its inputs to make the right judgement calls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI can arguably build the entire solution given a PRD and it might work for a lot of use cases but given its limitations, you still need a human in the loop to review and guide the solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;ai-as-an-intern-or-junior-developer&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ai-as-an-intern-or-junior-developer&quot; aria-label=&quot;ai as an intern or junior developer permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;AI as an intern or junior developer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any work you can define and scope well and assign to a junior developer can be done by an AI. Basically, these are tasks where there is enough detailing, there is low ambiguity and easily verifiable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;ai-as-a-sparring-partner&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ai-as-a-sparring-partner&quot; aria-label=&quot;ai as a sparring partner permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;AI as a sparring partner&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you want to analyse tradeoffs, discuss multiple approaches to a solution, LLMs with their information retrieval and reasoning can be a good way to bounce ideas, explore different solution spaces before settling in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;role-collapse&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#role-collapse&quot; aria-label=&quot;role collapse permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Role collapse&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI is clearly “lowering the floor and raising the ceiling”. It reduces the entry point for you to pick up tasks and can raise the quality of the output if wielded correctly as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I take up tasks, the roles that were created earlier to un-bottleneck the slowest task of actually writing software namely: business analysis, UI design, armchair software architecture is collapsing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Effective teams will have Product managers vibecoding POCs and mock ups for early customer feedback while developers will require lesser spoonfeeding of detailed tickets with AI filling in the gaps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This can be seen in orgs which now have a “forward deployed engineer” role that works with the customer and “business” directly, identifies problems and then builds the solution like AI agents using AI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;durable-skills&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#durable-skills&quot; aria-label=&quot;durable skills permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Durable Skills&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what are the durable skills to build on in the age of AI assisted software development? Those will be skills that make the human complement well with AI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Code monkeys who just get by glueing APIs and slinging UI code will be eaten by AI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, deep skills like critial thinking and analytical skills, foundational knowledge of algorithms, system design, breadth of experience with various architectures, design patterns, learnability etc will become premium - because these will still be required to collaborate effectively and draw the optimal output from AI. As Kent Beck says &lt;a href=&quot;https://newsletter.pragmaticengineer.com/p/tdd-ai-agents-and-coding-with-kent&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;“AI is an unpredictable genie who grants wishes”&lt;/a&gt; and you need to be careful and thorough with what you wish for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While anyone can vibe code a tool for personal use, a software that will be used by thousands of organizations or millions of users will have different contexts and considerations - blanks that can only be filled in by someone who knows what they are building and how to wield AI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;t-shaped-is-back&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#t-shaped-is-back&quot; aria-label=&quot;t shaped is back permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;T-shaped is back&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A T-shaped engineer is a professional with deep expertise in one field (the vertical bar of the T) and a broad knowledge base across many other disciplines (the horizontal bar). This combination of specialized knowledge and versatile skills allows them to tackle complex problems, collaborate effectively, and adapt to a constantly changing technical landscape. They are highly valuable in cross-functional teams, as they can contribute to their area of expertise while also helping with tasks in other domains, preventing project bottlenecks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the boom cycle rewarded even shallow or surface level skills, AI forces people to raise their own bar or be ever vulnerable to the next job cut.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proficiency in two or three programming language systems, putting a system in production, baking in observability, reliability, performance, systems design all become more important since AI has eaten the low hanging fruit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While chatting with an AI can give an illusion of picking something fast, real learning happens when you apply a concept in practice and learn from feedback.
So, the “10,000 hrs” would still hold good. AI might compress this by making the feedback loop faster and bring better learning examples but you still need to put in deliberate practice - leveraging AI when it makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, this is a very exciting time. Just as Software engineering was becoming boring with systems like cloud native architectures, platforms, tools and frameworks maturing over the recent years and AI provides the next big leap both in how software is built and what it can do.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[AI as a mirror]]></title><description><![CDATA[The foundation models offer a mirror to how we think]]></description><link>https://vishalnaik.org/posts/ai-as-a-mirror</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://vishalnaik.org/posts/ai-as-a-mirror</guid><pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 09:44:32 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Foundation models based on neural networks were inspired by the the biological brain. Now, remarkably, their behaviour offers a mirror into the patterns of the brain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;scaling-laws&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#scaling-laws&quot; aria-label=&quot;scaling laws permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Scaling laws&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With small training data and model size, the GPT models only generate gibberish. However as the data and model size increases, they start getting a lot better.
First generating random characters that look like words, then proper words but invalid sentences, then sentences that make sense and finally sentences that demonstrate reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As anyone who has seen a baby grow from birth can tell, the parallels are striking.
Much like the LLMs, better training data (rich experiences and time spent talking to and interacting with) makes for better learning in babies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;biases&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#biases&quot; aria-label=&quot;biases permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Biases&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With LLMs, you can see biases based on the data it was trained on. Feed more right wing / left wing / choose your ideology, and that’s what the model mirrors.
Similarly, your perspectives, mannerisms, behaviour indisputably etch on the brains of your children and those around you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;backpropagation&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#backpropagation&quot; aria-label=&quot;backpropagation permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Backpropagation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Backprop is the key to neural networks. It is basically a feedback loop which updates the models weights until it is able to predict on training data correctly. Makes you think about the various feedback loops around you and the feedback loops you create.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;learning-to-think&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#learning-to-think&quot; aria-label=&quot;learning to think permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Learning to think&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newyorker.com/tech/annals-of-technology/chatgpt-is-a-blurry-jpeg-of-the-web&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Ted Chiang on a NewYorker piece&lt;/a&gt; called ChatGPT a “blurry jpeg of the web” - basically a lossy compression of knowledge.
Initial models like upto GPT 3.5 gave the impression that that even if these models had knowledge, they didn’t have wisdom.
As &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.in/Siddhartha-Hermann-Hesse/dp/817234368X&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Siddhartha&lt;/a&gt; says to his friend Govinda, “Knowledge can be transferred but not wisdom.”
Wisdom is application of knowledge in the right context. Each of our brains are wired differently and while you can regurgitate knowledge, the interpretation, application and the reasoning of that will vary from one individual to another because we all have different weights and biases and neural connections.
Yet, methods like Chain-of-thought prompting, RL fine tuning etc can teach to “think”, atleast impart patterns of thinking.
Reinforcement learning takes the same approach of how you have practice problems in text books after a few examples. The model is “rewarded” for getting the steps and finally the answer right. Because, until you are able to answer questions, you haven’t truly grokked the subject.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;prediction-machines&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#prediction-machines&quot; aria-label=&quot;prediction machines permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Prediction machines&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LLMs were trivialised as next token predictors. It is after all how they work.
But the brain is similar in many ways. The brain is a prediction machine too. It is constantly trying to predict the state and anxiety is a state of not being able to predict well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perception is less about passively receiving the world and more about actively predicting it. The brain’s goal? Minimize surprise. When it predicts well, you feel in control; when it can’t, things get shaky. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/books/2021/aug/25/being-you-by-professor-anil-seth-review-the-exhilarating-new-science-of-consciousness&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Being You&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For e.g. we enjoy music because we are able to predict the next token in the rhythmic sequence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;language-as-the-key-to-thinking&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#language-as-the-key-to-thinking&quot; aria-label=&quot;language as the key to thinking permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Language as the key to Thinking&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Computers writing code or poetry or novels like humans was the last thing that perhaps people imagined in the AI roadmap.
It was far more realistic to imagine AIs solving for manual labor vs things that required higher order thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, LLMs demonstrated that grokking language by learning through vast amounts of text, does unlock higher order thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other species demonstrate reasoning abilities to solve problems but for higher order thinking, language seems to be the key and only humans have a true language center in the brain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a reason why GRE critical reasoning questions are in such a format.
Perhaps having a rich vocabulary is key to have a higher level of perception.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;South Asian philosophical traditions suggest that language is fundamental to how we perceive the world, and that learning new words can even shape our experiences. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bostonreview.net/articles/theres-a-word-for-that/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;There is a word for that&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;where-do-ai-models-go-from-here&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#where-do-ai-models-go-from-here&quot; aria-label=&quot;where do ai models go from here permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Where do AI models go from here?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LLMs are already better than most humans in problem solving, writing, critical thinking etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What are some interesting next steps?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;agency&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#agency&quot; aria-label=&quot;agency permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Agency&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LLMs for better or worse do not have a concept of “self”. Currently, they are all but stateless token predictors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But add memory, self preservation and other goals, it can get interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.templeton.org/discoveries/agency-in-biology&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;What is Agency?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;working-in-groups&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#working-in-groups&quot; aria-label=&quot;working in groups permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Working in groups&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is fascinating that it is not Neanderthals, the sub species of Homo erectus which had bigger brains that ended up dominating but Homosapiens who apparently were in the Goldilock’s zone of “just right” social dynamics and brain size.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps LLMs will also hit scaling limits where there is diminishing returns with model size and it is more efficient to be “distributed” and have different models collaborate.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The AI Age]]></title><description><![CDATA[Entering the Age of AI and what it feels like]]></description><link>https://vishalnaik.org/posts/entering-the-age-of-ai</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://vishalnaik.org/posts/entering-the-age-of-ai</guid><pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 06:10:32 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Small recap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just 5 years back we were in the middle of Covid. Lots of lives were lost. People were in lockdown for many months and doom scrolling.
Yet, somehow, humanity gathered itself, organised, not only invented a vaccine but also magically got it delivered to billions of humans around the world. We survived and some of us working in tech actually thrived.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Covid put a lot of digital tech in focus. Lot of money was thrown around. Tech became super hot. And then it melted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Offline took over again. People realised the valuations were way out of propotions. Meanwhile, interest rates started climbing and put pressure on margins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, there was a correction and we transitioned quitely from “Work From Home Forever”, “The Great Resignation”,  “Quiet Quitting” etc to layoffs and “Back To Office - Whether you like it or not”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But something was brewing on the side which everyone first ignored , then laughed about and then it became so good that you hope it doesn’t fight you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, the AIs, the LLMs have gotten so good that if you aren’t using them OR building on them, then you are going to be on the wrong side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But let’s cut to the chase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-is-knowledge-work-heck-our-lives-going-to-change&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#how-is-knowledge-work-heck-our-lives-going-to-change&quot; aria-label=&quot;how is knowledge work heck our lives going to change permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;How is knowledge work, heck, our lives going to change?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LLMs are forcing us to deeply introspect the nature of our work and what it is we really do. If a task can be relegated to an LLM, it will be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several good reads on this from AI as a copilot to the end of programming altogether to a more far reaching view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vivekhaldar.com/articles/re--why-i-don-t-use-copilot/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Re: Why I don’t use Copilot&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cacm.acm.org/opinion/the-end-of-programming/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;The End Of Programming&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://darioamodei.com/machines-of-loving-grace&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Machines of Loving Grace&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things are still unfolding. Right now atleast, it feels like a calm before the storm, or the next big AI model.
It maybe that AI scaling has hit a wall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, the focus has shifted to applications &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sequoiacap.com/article/generative-ai-act-two/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Generative AI’s Act Two&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the interesting ways to look at it is through the lens of humans “in the loop”, “on the loop”  and “off the loop”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI as a co-pilot is going to grow. It can become more effective, more personalised as a “Pair Programmer” than even a human.
That is going to have far reaching consequences to jobs as we know it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Entry level SWE are already &lt;a href=&quot;https://vivekhaldar.com/articles/llms-eat-entry-level-swes/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;feeling the heat&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we look at how autopilot tech on planes change pilot training and skill requirements is any indication, knowledge work that &lt;em&gt;needs&lt;/em&gt; a human in the loop will also change similarly with AI copilots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://chatgpt.com/share/6702bc9c-844c-8012-90bf-08f43e00c39f&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;https://chatgpt.com/share/6702bc9c-844c-8012-90bf-08f43e00c39f&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While autopilot has changed pilot training by shifting some focus to system management and human-machine interaction, the fundamentals of flying—manual control, situational awareness, and emergency response—remain critical. The role of pilots has evolved into more of a systems manager, but their responsibility for the safety of the flight is as crucial as ever. Autopilot is a tool, not a replacement, and pilot training ensures that aviators are ready to handle both automated and manual flight situations effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that can’t be a bad thing. Right?&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Thoughts On Remote]]></title><description><![CDATA[Remote work has tradeoffs and must be understood before applying it voluntarily]]></description><link>https://vishalnaik.org/posts/thoughts-on-remote</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://vishalnaik.org/posts/thoughts-on-remote</guid><pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 18:40:32 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;(Incomplete draft)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;on-remote&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#on-remote&quot; aria-label=&quot;on remote permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;On Remote&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last 16 years in tech, I have had the opportunity to work remotely on several occassions, notwithstanding the Covid imposed remote work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IT services companies notoriously don’t encouraged work from home especially on time based billing projects, and it used to be on discretion. Product companies on the other hand, were always more relaxed on remote because outcome matters more than output and there are no timesheets to fill anyways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the last 1 year Covid imposed remote work wherever possible and software development particularly is well suited because you just need a laptop and internet connection to start working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case Covid has changed perspectives on remote work forever - from outright skeptics who had to accept that it was possible to productive remotely to the pro-WFH rebel who now craves to go to the office :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-remote-work-enabled&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#what-remote-work-enabled&quot; aria-label=&quot;what remote work enabled permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;What remote work enabled&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save commute times (or reduce if working from nearby coworking space)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More time for family and kids and better satisfaction in that sphere&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lesser interruptions if you are able to block out Slack and other notifications and therefore larger chunks of time to focus on tasks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reduce energy depletion for introverts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-an-office-enables-but-is-challenging-in-remote&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#what-an-office-enables-but-is-challenging-in-remote&quot; aria-label=&quot;what an office enables but is challenging in remote permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;What an office enables but is challenging in remote&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Meetings - just harder to run with a lot of people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Face to face interactions that build trust and team work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Huddles to brainstorm on an idea or tech design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mentoring new developers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Physical isolation that allows one to keep away from distractions and other errands when working from home.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Team building through water cooler conversations and group activities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Energy refueling for extroverts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gauge well being of your team and employees and help them if required&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shared understanding&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;other-remote-challenges&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#other-remote-challenges&quot; aria-label=&quot;other remote challenges permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Other remote challenges&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Zoom fatigue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slack overload&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;compensating-for-gaps-in-remote&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#compensating-for-gaps-in-remote&quot; aria-label=&quot;compensating for gaps in remote permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Compensating for gaps in remote&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meeting memos&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amazon’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@Elabor8/amazons-shift-from-presentation-culture-to-memo-culture-and-what-you-can-learn-from-it-a44f6db2c864&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;unique meeting style&lt;/a&gt; has been getting a lot of attention. Some of the immediate takeaways like having a clear agenda, documenting all the required context and references for the meeting can go a long way to make meetings effective and efficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emphasise Documentation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A writing culture for everything from product requirements to design decisions (e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://adr.github.io/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;ADR&lt;/a&gt;) to process and HOWTOs help a lot in preserving context that would have been tribal knowledge in the team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use tools like Quip / Notion that promote documentation
Slack is great for real time context sharing but a poor medium for a knowledge base. Tools like Quip, Notion etc. which faciliate conversations around documents, go a long way to not only enable documentation but also preserve context. This automatically promotes documentation around a context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google Docs with its comments feature is good too but its doesn’t do a great job with comments. For e.g. the interactions on top of a comment are limited and others cannot upvote a comment or react to it. The author can resolve a comment and it is then lost - so, I haven’t found google docs very nice for collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Avoid Slack fights&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slack can be great upto a point but discussions can devolve into heated arguments and regurgitation of the same points, much like keyboard warriors you come across on internet forums and WhatsApp groups. When this happens its better to get everyone with strong opinions into a meeting to have a more productive discussion and conclude.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Build a shared understanding in the team&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider a developer that takes an approach to implement something and submits a pull request. However, other reviewers push a lot of feedback on design gaps and change suggestions - this can be demoralizing for the developer besides slowing down the team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, for major changes, make sure that there is a shared understanding on the high level design before implementation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same applies for QAs and Product too. This is where weekly iteration planning meetings to review work for next week are useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Pull requests work best when there is *already* a shared understanding of what/why/how. &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/GgZrPqHvT6&quot;&gt;https://t.co/GgZrPqHvT6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Vishal Naik (@vishalmanohar) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/vishalmanohar/status/1370584611240046594?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;March 13, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-remote-work-demands-from-indiviuals&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#what-remote-work-demands-from-indiviuals&quot; aria-label=&quot;what remote work demands from indiviuals permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;What remote work demands from indiviuals&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Great work ethic&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main concern for engineering manager regarding remote work is : “I am sure those with a good work ethic will work but there are a few people in the org who aren’t just that committed and won’t pull their weight if they know they aren’t being monitored.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the office automatically creates a range of office hours to work, the freedom of working remotely means that you get to work whenever you want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this freedom also comes with a responsibility that you do work and are productive for a minimum set of hours everyday. If you are not able to for whatever reason, then the team must be informed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A great work ethic is a pre-requisite for remote work because a slacker will just take abuse of the system and become a drag to the whole team. Therefore, the org must also have mechanisms to monitor remote work  effectiveness and ensure perpetual slackers are weeded
out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shape your own environment to be productive
When you are at an office, you are naturally in “work” mode and just seeing other people at work primes everyone else to work and be productive. So whether it is a boring task that just needs to be done, or you don’t feel very motivated to work in the beginning of the day, you can still end up being productive thanks to the environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, when working from home you are on your own and need to create an environment that is great for work - whatever it means to the individual. For e.g. it might be setting up a quiet space or a workstation or reducing non work interruptions etc as much as possibly. Or, it might also be arranging for lunch which would otherwise have been provided at the office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hanselminutes has a great podcast &lt;a href=&quot;https://hanselminutes.simplecast.com/episodes/surviving-as-a-remote-tech-employee-with-jayson-j-phillips-G0lphUL1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;on this&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monitoring remote work&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Managing by walking around” isn’t possible when working remote obviously. When you are in an office, you can get a pulse of how well a team is working, who are the playmakers and who might need support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For e.g., you might see a senior mentoring a new person on the team or someone leading a design discussion or another person helping someone else troubleshoot something. Or you might just see the story wall and notice that a developer is stuck on a low complexity story for many days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With remote, the team will need to have mechanisms to compensate for the above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Review code commits periodically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Review pull request review time - if there are too many pending PRs in the queue its not a good sign. Maybe there is too much dependency on one lead developer to review the PR.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One-on-One meetings every week for new folks and atleast once in 2 weeks for the rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there is too much back and forth on Pull requests and Jira tickets, its sign that there is a lack of shared understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ensure there is no single point of failure in the team for each aspect. For e.g. if the team relies on the same person everytime to troubleshoot a production issue or to perform infra changes, this needs to be addressed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Excellent communication skills&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Empathy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proactive Doer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;hybrid&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#hybrid&quot; aria-label=&quot;hybrid permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Hybrid&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Post Covid, whenever that happens, a hybrid approach where a team can work together for 2-3 days a week and then remotely for the remaining 2 days seems ideal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This way, a team can decide to have all their planned meetings and huddles that are suited for face to face on the office days and while benefitting from remote work on the rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;interviewing-for-remote&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#interviewing-for-remote&quot; aria-label=&quot;interviewing for remote permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Interviewing for remote&lt;/h3&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Org Scaling Antipatterns]]></title><description><![CDATA[Scaling from a 5-10 dev org to a 50-100 org can be messy if not calibrated.]]></description><link>https://vishalnaik.org/posts/org-scaling-antipatterns</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://vishalnaik.org/posts/org-scaling-antipatterns</guid><pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 18:40:32 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;(Incomplete draft)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transitioning from Phase 1 of a start up where you have 1-10 member dev org to Phase 2 where you have 20-100+ dev org is a huge step and below are a few things I have observed in my consulting engagements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;phase-1&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#phase-1&quot; aria-label=&quot;phase 1 permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Phase 1&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Phase 1 is the validation stage of the idea or building the product around a few early customers to demonstrate product market fit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this phase, you are ideally a small, nimble, self selected, high performance team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During this phase, its all about iterating fast, onboarding customers quickly, building POCs for customer demos and delighting early customers with quick turnaround times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no time for detailed requirement documents or iteration planning meetings, detailed estimation or the agile rituals and so the days can be unstructured (coding away a feature one moment to fixing a prod issue in the other to switching to a new priority for a customer demo for the next day) and there is a lot of ambiguity in the requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if you have been able to build a team of effective engineers from your network who are skilled in their craft and there is a high degree of trust, you can get away with not doing all of that and focus instead on building the product and getting that early traction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this phase, it is critical to have engineers that have the following attributes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Founder mindset&lt;/strong&gt; - for e.g. is highly self motivated, understands the criticality of different tasks and prioritises accordingly, understands the WHYs etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Full stack engineer&lt;/strong&gt; - e.g. can work on frontend and backend with acceptable quality of work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proactive Doer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strong Work Ethic&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;phase-2&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#phase-2&quot; aria-label=&quot;phase 2 permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Phase 2&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is often the phase where the company has validated the product with early customers, raised more capital and its priority is to expand its capabilties to service even more customers and use cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This also means growing your dev org and adding more engineers to the team. But what got you till here won’t get you there and recognizing this and adapting
is necessary to avoid &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/problem-opportunity-organizational-debt-bharath-jayaraman/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;organizational debt&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this stage, things change dramatically for the dev org.
With each new member the lines of communication between members grow exponentially and beyond 5-7 poeople in the team, there needs to be hierarchy set up to bring some sanity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn.shortpixel.ai/client/q_lossy,ret_img/https://getlighthouse.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/lines-of-communication-stackoverflow-1024x953.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;https://getlighthouse.com/blog/developing-leaders-team-grows-big/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There also needs to be derisking of individual dependency or &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bus_factor&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;bus factor&lt;/a&gt; because the stakes are higher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then, there are usually compliance requirements to be met for bigger customers, need for UX consistency across the product, which means subject matter experts for SecOps and UX.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So after a certain point, the large team needs to be organized into smaller teams around modules. The roles and responsibilities need to be explicily called out and processes for everything from code repo branching to PR guidelines to QA and release process, to production support and access needs to be defined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;antipattern-1-rampup-before-achieving-pmf&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#antipattern-1-rampup-before-achieving-pmf&quot; aria-label=&quot;antipattern 1 rampup before achieving pmf permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Antipattern 1: Rampup before achieving PMF&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;antipattern-2-hiring-fast-firing-slow&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#antipattern-2-hiring-fast-firing-slow&quot; aria-label=&quot;antipattern 2 hiring fast firing slow permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Antipattern 2: Hiring fast, firing slow&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Phase 1, the hiring is usually from close networks and there is no formal hiring process or interview. The people have already worked with one another and there is already trust established.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyone not pulling their weight is plainly visible and it is easier to let go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, beyond a size, the company needs to recruit second or third degree referrals and without sufficient vetting,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;lack-of-standardized-hiring-process&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#lack-of-standardized-hiring-process&quot; aria-label=&quot;lack of standardized hiring process permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Lack of standardized hiring process&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;short-circuited-process-for-referals&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#short-circuited-process-for-referals&quot; aria-label=&quot;short circuited process for referals permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Short circuited process for referals&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the team are getting set up, given how hard it is to find good developers, sometimes you might hire someone who doesn’t have the technical depth based on interview feedback but still don’t want to lose them because maybe they can build those CRUD UIs or other areas in the app which don’t need much tech chops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;antipattern-3-feature-factory&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#antipattern-3-feature-factory&quot; aria-label=&quot;antipattern 3 feature factory permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Antipattern 3: Feature Factory&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;antipattern-4-structurelessness&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#antipattern-4-structurelessness&quot; aria-label=&quot;antipattern 4 structurelessness permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Antipattern 4: Structurelessness&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A close knit small org doesn’t need a lot of structure because there is a lot of trust and the communication lines are fewer. But beyond a team size of 10 and above, the lack of structure starts becoming an impediment.
Also suggested reading: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jofreeman.com/joreen/tyranny.htm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Tyranny of structurelessness&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;antipattern-5-lack-of-career-ladder&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#antipattern-5-lack-of-career-ladder&quot; aria-label=&quot;antipattern 5 lack of career ladder permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Antipattern 5: Lack of career ladder&lt;/h2&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Types of Technical Debt]]></title><description><![CDATA[Understanding the taxonomy of technical debt can help anticipate and plan before last due date.]]></description><link>https://vishalnaik.org/posts/types-of-technical-debt</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://vishalnaik.org/posts/types-of-technical-debt</guid><pubDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2021 18:40:32 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Technical Debt is a phrase that is most often used to refer to shortcomings in the software from a technical perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The metaphor is attributed to Ward Cunningham, &lt;a href=&quot;http://wiki.c2.com/?WardExplainsDebtMetaphor&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;who explained it as&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The explanation I gave to my boss, and this was financial software, was a financial analogy I called “the debt metaphor”. And that said that if we failed to make our program align with what we then understood to be the proper way to think about our financial objects, then we were gonna continually stumble over that disagreement and that would slow us down which was like paying interest on a loan.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While technical debt is most often used to refer to the design and code quality issues, it also has a broader applicability and being aware of the different types of debt can help plan and prioritize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;types-of-technical-debt&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#types-of-technical-debt&quot; aria-label=&quot;types of technical debt permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Types of Technical Debt&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;quality-of-code-debt&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#quality-of-code-debt&quot; aria-label=&quot;quality of code debt permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Quality of Code Debt&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the usage of the term technical debt refers to issues with code quality.
Below are some of the things that drags down quality of code:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;examples&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#examples&quot; aria-label=&quot;examples permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Examples:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Code Smells&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are the “Code Smells” listed exhaustively in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://martinfowler.com/books/refactoring.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Refactoring&lt;/a&gt; book. Smelly code is not just an eye sore for anyone who reads it but is akin to a high amp resistor to enhance features on top of, besides being a source of defects and an anchor for developer morale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Duplication of business logic&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most often done for a “quick and dirty” fix but also can be caused by lack of context with the developer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Business logic duplication often creates a whack-a-mole pattern of defects where each fix introduces an inconsitency in behaviour from its duplicates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not all duplication incurs the same cost. E.g. Duplicating business logic like tax calculation in an invoicing module can be very costly since it can be source of bugs, whereas duplication of a small utility method although imperfect is not a big deal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hardcoding instead of driving by config&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For e.g. using a custom logic against a customer identity to meet their immediate requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often used for quick fixes or implemented for proof of concept but if not attended to, can languish and affect maintainability as the customer base grows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lack Of Tests&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Test coverage is what gives confidence to change code and lack of sufficient coverage, atleast in the important workflows of the code is a huge debt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hard to Read&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How easy is it for a new developer to understand a piece of code and relate it to business understanding? Does the code convey the intent properly?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is complex domain logic encapsulated using Domain Driven Design?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is the code organized in a structured manner around modules?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How much of tribal knowledge is required for a new team member to make a low complexity change on their first week of work?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lack of Observability&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you able to observe what the system is doing in a production environment?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lack of logging in the code, lack of auditing user actions can severely impede maintainability and slow down resolution of customer issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;improving-code-quality&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#improving-code-quality&quot; aria-label=&quot;improving code quality permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Improving Code Quality&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Code quality related issues become apparent once an application is in production and being enhanced. This can be visible in terms of defects or customer support tickets or unusally long times to make small changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Code quality issues can be budgeted whenever there is a change in the related area either to fix a defect or to enhance a business logic. For e.g. in a story or a ticket to enhance a feature, the team can also highlight the issues with the code that needs to be addressed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Observability issues must be fixed as and when they are detected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Automated code quality checks like PMD in java or Rubocop in Rails or JSLint in Javascript can help surface issues during development and can be a developer aid apart from code reviews.
However, quality of code is a function of the level of the craftsmanship on the team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides pairing, doing refactoring workshops, &lt;a href=&quot;https://martinfowler.com/books/refactoring.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Refactoring&lt;/a&gt; book reading, DHH’s set of videos on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wXaC0YvDgIo&amp;#x26;list=PL9wALaIpe0Py6E_oHCgTrD6FvFETwJLlx&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;“Writing software well”&lt;/a&gt; have helped me to impress the importance of code quality and drive changes especially for new developers and teams that have been very tactical while coding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstraction-debt&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#abstraction-debt&quot; aria-label=&quot;abstraction debt permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Abstraction Debt&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The primarily leverage in software or a machine versus doing something manually is the ability to build abstractions so that the same thing can be used as many times in different contexts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider a hardware fastenter like a nut and bolt. This primitive can be used to join parts together and is a fundamental building block in artifacts. This can be used to build tools which is then used to build even complex tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Likewise, software is composed using multiple primitives, which leads to a complex building block on top of which more complex things can be built.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well written software recognizes commonality of requirements and abstracts behaviour and concepts to provide the right primitives and abstractions on which more complex behaviours can be built.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Poorly written software often is a big ball of mud with rote code used to do the same things in different places and reveals itself when even small changes require a lot of effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Example - not using a layered design and making things reusable. Consider a shopping cart application. An order can be created from multiple sources - cart, special offer, subscription, external API etc. Well structured code will have a single internal API to create an order from different sources and not have multiple APIs for the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a consulting engagement, working with an enterprise SaaS application, the reporting module did not have any abstraction for basic things like server-side pagination and filtering or role based filters. Each new report would get hand coded in its own way and over time the report count grew to over a 100. In the early stages of that enterprise product, there was not much data and this was passable. But as the data began to grow, performance issues due to lack of server side pagination revealed itself and these reports had to be re-written from the ground up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern application frameworks like Spring Boot, Django, Rails already take care of providing web app primitives for HTTP request routing, database access, file storage, emails etc. But any non-trivial application will need custom abstractions to create leverage in software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deferred abstractions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, an abstraction can be deferred until there is better clarity on requirements and use cases or until the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cost_of_delay&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;cost of delay&lt;/a&gt; is not viable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s say in an enterprise product, each customer has complex data processing rules.  Not having an abstraction like a DSL or configurability in the rules is a debt because ability to express these rules easily is a much needed abstraction here. However, if the complexities and future needs can’t be anticipated at the early stage with the first few customers, it might make sense to implement them using custom code for each customer without building a custom DSL or using a rule engine.
Here you are trying to avoid the cost of the wrong abstraction which can be much higher than the benefit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A feature debt can also be a cause of the missing abstraction. Consider an example where each customer for enterprise product expects a custom invoice template. An Invoice Template Builder UI is ideal but depending on the product and the number of customers, this can be deferred and instead built as custom template per customer if there are more important features to focus on until it becomes a pain point. Here, the cost of delay is an important metric to measure if this should be done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Missing abstractions are usually due to lack of tech leadership in the team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;preventing-abstraction-debt&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#preventing-abstraction-debt&quot; aria-label=&quot;preventing abstraction debt permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Preventing Abstraction Debt&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstractions provide the primary leverage in software development. Developers must constantly evaluate when something needs to be abstracted at the time of development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be wary of the cost of building the wrong abstraction. The cost to dismantle it and replace will be much more expensive than deferring it and when there is better context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a shortcut is used intentionally, call it out with the rest of your team. Use comments in the code to let other developers know about the context and how you think this might need to change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the related feature evolves, evaluate whether it is time to put in a proper abstraction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cost_of_delay&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Cost of delay&lt;/a&gt; is a great measure to priotize work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teams must have technical leaders who are able to think at a system level and consider these tradeoffs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;dependency-upgrade-debt&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#dependency-upgrade-debt&quot; aria-label=&quot;dependency upgrade debt permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Dependency Upgrade Debt&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Code doesn’t exist in isolation. Any non-trivial software application will have many many third party libraries and packages they depend on to build the software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is everything from the language version, to application framework version and other libraries used to accomplish specific tasks. And, each of them are also evolving over time just like your software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This tends to be one of the most overlooked aspect of tech debt.
But the cost can be crippling especially for an application built on a dynamic language like Ruby and Python AND with low test coverage - where it is much harder to upgrade the language version and the application framework. Upgrades like Python 2 to 3 where there are a lot of breaking features is a nightmare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Java world also, the 6 month release cadence has meant faster rollout of new features and shorter end of life cycles for support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dependency upgrade debt is the cost you have to pay for not upgrading your dependency version periodically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cost of dependency upgrade debt&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much bigger risk and effort to upgrade when the version distance is high.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Online community support for a constantly evolving package version dwindles over time. Consider React Native. A lot of issues on their Github and Stackoverflow are so dependent on the version of the framework that if you have to overcome an issue that you are facing, it means you have to upgrade to a more recent version to even report the issue and get help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Older version API documentation might be discared. And with that you might even lose the documentation required to migrate from your current version to the next version incrementally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Miss out on bug fixes, new features, performance improvements, security vulnerability fixes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Risk of forced upgrade at the worst possible time. Consider, you run into a major performance issue that is getting a lot of customer tickets and you trace this to a dependency that hasn’t been updated for many years. You discover that the issue has been on a new major version of the software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inability to upgrade one package for a feature because it needs a higher version of another package. e.g. a lot of Django packages are compatible with the specific version of Django and you can’t upgrade a package without upgrading Django itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;tackling-dependency-upgrade-debt&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#tackling-dependency-upgrade-debt&quot; aria-label=&quot;tackling dependency upgrade debt permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Tackling Dependency Upgrade Debt&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Review dependency upgrades periodically - atleast once in a quarter and create action items.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use tools like &lt;a href=&quot;https://dependabot.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;dependabot&lt;/a&gt; to automate dependency upgrades.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep the team aware of new releases in core packages by subscribing to RSS feeds in your Slack channel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;infrastructure-debt&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#infrastructure-debt&quot; aria-label=&quot;infrastructure debt permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Infrastructure Debt&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like software dependency upgrade debt, your infra also needs constant upkeep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider, Postgres database or elastic search service or a message queue. Each of these infrastructure pieces are also evolving constantly - which is good in terms of features and performance but it also means they need to be on your radar for upgrades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cloud Services are also constantly evolving with a slew of new features, capabilities and products being announced every year - whether it AWS, Azure or Google Cloud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each upgrade is an opportunity to leverage better features, performance or price that can improve your product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cost of insfrastructure debt&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Same as dependency debts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Even lesser optionality on managed cloud services - for e.g. RDS on AWS stops support for older end of life versions of Postgres/RDS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;tackling-infrastructure-debt&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#tackling-infrastructure-debt&quot; aria-label=&quot;tackling infrastructure debt permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Tackling Infrastructure Debt&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Similar to dependency upgrade debt, infrastructure upgrades must be reviewed periodically within the team.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using containers to set up dependencies like DB, ElasticSearch etc locally and on CI can provide a lot of leverage to upgrade versions and go back and forth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify and groom expertise in the team around key infrastructure. For e.g. if your product uses MongoDB, Kubernetes, ElasticSearch, each of these should have members who are proficient in them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use a Skill Matrix in the team to identify expertise gaps and review periodically to make sure that the gaps are closing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;closing-thoughts&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#closing-thoughts&quot; aria-label=&quot;closing thoughts permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Closing Thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Technical debt comes in many forms. Recognizing each and planning for it helps in managing it proactively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Technical debt is a function of the quality of people in the team.
Are they passionate about their craft?
Do they have a good work ethic?
Are they curious to learn new things?
Are they able to communicate to the leadership about technical debt and influence decisions?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, there is no substitute for experience and expertise in the team.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Lessons from a Tennis Class]]></title><description><![CDATA[A recent experience as a student of tennis brought some perspectives on mentoring and what it feels like to be a student again.]]></description><link>https://vishalnaik.org/posts/tennis-lessons</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://vishalnaik.org/posts/tennis-lessons</guid><pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2019 22:40:32 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I started playing Tennis under a coach recently. I had donned a coachee role after a long time and one of the first things that came to mind when it started was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The coach makes such a big difference. The individual attention and personal feedback and suggestions are helping immensely. Why don’t we have a coach for professional work?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ‘coachee’ experience triggered some perspectives:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a humbling (and fumbling) experience taking the first steps to a game I hadn’t played before. I really appreciated the patience shown by the coaches to correct the mistakes step by step until a stroke was improved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is easy to forget how difficult it was the first time once you gain a lot of experience and not show the same empathy when you become a mentor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coach seemed to know that you should not overwhelm someone with too much feedback and gave it incrementally and at the right time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a lead or mentor, it is our job is to give feedback to help someone improve. But the timing and tone are as important as the objectivity of the feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The junior coach would sometimes keep repeating the same feedback to no avail at times — “bend your knees or turn your upper body more to play a shot. You need to get into position quickly so that you have enough time. You need to improve footwork”. The senior coach would watch and later prescribe warm-up routines and stretches to enhance flexibility and footwork or improve stamina.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a mentor, you need to listen carefully and look at things from the perspective of the mentee — only then can you connect to the root cause and solve the problem effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a beginner in the game, I would initially try to quickly wrap up warm-up exercises so I could get to the court and start playing. However, I would notice senior players who would do 1 hour of intensive warm-up and exercise before even picking up the racquet. And when you saw them playing in the court later, it was clear why that prep work is essential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Foundations matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;True learning is not just about learning the latest cool framework but also having a deep understanding of how things work and the basics like data structures, algorithms, compiler construction — We might not need this 90% of the time but that 10% use case where you have to build an abstraction, these foundational skills make a huge difference.
I later remembered this article I had read many years back — &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2011/10/03/personal-best&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;“Top athletes and singers have coaches. Should you?”&lt;/a&gt; by Atul Gawande.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, a personal coach in the professional realm in software engineering might be a tall order. But luckily in this field, there are several ways one can get guidance when you cannot arrange a personal coach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pair program with seniors in the team or company&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If your company has a mentorship program, take advantage of it and meet your mentor every month to discuss&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read code from top quality open source projects. Contribute to open-source projects that you are interested in&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Follow experts in the area of your interest on Twitter — keep abreast of emerging trends&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read foundational books — there are enough essential reading lists out there.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get online training — egghead, purelyfunctional.tv— lots of online classes where you can also interact with the trainer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Attend conferences, build a network of people you can rely on when in doubt.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[In Praise Of Angular 2]]></title><description><![CDATA[Angular is a great improvement over AngularJS and can be a great choice for building single page apps, if you want a batteries included framework.]]></description><link>https://vishalnaik.org/posts/in-praise-of-angular</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://vishalnaik.org/posts/in-praise-of-angular</guid><pubDate>Sat, 11 Mar 2017 22:40:32 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;At my startup, our core application is built on AngularJS (1.x) and it was chosen for various reasons at that time. However, when there was a need to build additional applications last December, I was sure that I didn’t want to use Angular 1.x for those — mainly because it wasn’t satisfying nor fun to work on it especially with new and better alternatives like React and Angular 2 becoming mature.
I chose Angular 2 and I couldn’t be happier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;###Choosing Angular 2 vs React
For me, it eventually came down to choosing an end to end framework that provides all the functionalities required for a Single Page App versus choosing a library that builds views and leaving a lot of open decisions to make on view routing, an http service, architectural pattern, a build tool and others.
While the latter was tempting because it would have been fun to explore and choose different tools for each purpose, being in a lean start-up didn’t afford that option and we chose Angular 2 and a few months down the line, I couldn’t be happier with the choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;###Feels a lot like AngularJS but 10x better
At a first glance, Angular 2 is bound to feel alien with the annotation heavy declarations and TypeScript syntax but play with it a little and if you have worked with Angular 1.x, you will soon relate to the same patterns like directives, HTML templates, dependency injection etc and ramp up pretty quickly. The egghead tutorial on Angular2 fundamentals really helped too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;##What makes it 10x better?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;###Component driven design
With AngularJS, directives were the way to component-ize views so that they are modular for better organization, readability and reusability. However, the tendency in AngularJS was always to have fat Ng Controllers. With Angular 2, components (essentially directives) are the primary building blocks and there is no choice between an ng include controller or directives leading to a consistent pattern that is encouraged by the framework. In effect this led to much better modularity in the codebase.
State propagation is also much cleaner and explicit — where instead of using two-way binding of AngularJS, you use what is called as Event Emitters to signal state changes. Event Emitters and the Angular 2 http service use RxJS Observables which is a great fit!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;###Angular CLI
If there was one thing that quickly pulled me into Angular 2 when I was just trying it, it was the Angular CLI which makes it super easy to get started building Angular apps. Angular CLI takes away all the chores you would have to do building a single page app — project skeleton set up, test framework setup (unit test and e2e), build set up, minification, environment configuration — so that you can focus on building features. The CLI uses webpack under the hood and if you want more control, you can always eject out of the CLI and use webpack directly — although I haven’t had to do this yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;###TypeScript
Using typed Javascript is a joy on great IDE. Refactoring support, auto-complete features are much better with the type information but more importantly, using types enhances readability and the maintainability of the code. I have found myself diving into a codebase after a gap and found it at home primarily because the data structures were explicit. And TypeScript being a superset of JS, there isn’t a steep curve either and you can learn and discover things as you go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;###Performance&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Angular 2 was designed to be mobile friendly and as such is faster than Angular 1.x and with AOT, it is a lot faster now with very little perceptible lag for initial rendering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;###Angular Universal
Server side rendering is still a thing if you to be friendly to Search Engines and Angular Universal framework makes it possible to set up pre-rendering pretty quickly. I haven’t used this so far but intend to soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, Angular 2 is a significant improvement on AngularJS and is a great option if you just want to run with an opinionated end to end framework.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Baking In Configurability - Product Rewrite Story - Part 2]]></title><description><![CDATA[A real world blog series on a do-or-die product rewrite engagement from the trenches. This part talks about how we addressed the requirements of configurability and extensibility in the core of the platform.]]></description><link>https://vishalnaik.org/posts/product-rewrite-story-part-2</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://vishalnaik.org/posts/product-rewrite-story-part-2</guid><pubDate>Mon, 25 Jul 2016 22:40:32 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;A multi-tenant financial product that we were building needed to be highly configurable and extensible.
Read more on how we &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sahajsoft.com/blog/product-rewrite-story-part-2/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;baked in configurability at the heart of that platform&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Innovate or Perish - Product Rewrite Story - Part 1]]></title><description><![CDATA[A real world blog series on a do-or-die product rewrite engagement from the trenches.]]></description><link>https://vishalnaik.org/posts/product-rewrite-story-part-1</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://vishalnaik.org/posts/product-rewrite-story-part-1</guid><pubDate>Tue, 12 Jul 2016 22:40:32 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;It is great when products reach product market fit but if their architecture doesn’t enable them to onboard and service customers effectively, those companies will not able to scale their business beyond the few handful customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, a rewrite of the core product is called for to accomodate the business requirements from a fresh perspective.
In such cases, the technical effort is akin to replacing the engine of a airplane in flight, because neither the customers nor the competition is waiting for you to catch up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read more on the experience working on such an effort on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sahajsoft.com/blog/product-rewrite-story-part-1/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Sahaj engineering blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Architecting For Continuous Delivery]]></title><description><![CDATA[Continuous Delivery is not just about selecting the right tools. The application should also be architected in a way to make it effective.]]></description><link>https://vishalnaik.org/posts/architecting-for-continuous-delivery</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://vishalnaik.org/posts/architecting-for-continuous-delivery</guid><pubDate>Fri, 20 Nov 2015 22:40:32 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;This is my post on ThoughtWorks Insights on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thoughtworks.com/insights/blog/architecting-continuous-delivery&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Architecting for Continuous Delivery&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;[Best of 2016] What is the real essence of &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/ContinuousDelivery?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#ContinuousDelivery&lt;/a&gt;? &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/vishalmanohar?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@vishalmanohar&lt;/a&gt; explains here &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/RWkR6BUlYA&quot;&gt;https://t.co/RWkR6BUlYA&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/IZQxZWM1dI&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/IZQxZWM1dI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; ThoughtWorks (@thoughtworks) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/thoughtworks/status/814216608096854016?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;December 28, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Trunk Based Development With Deployment Pipelines]]></title><description><![CDATA[The popular 'Gitflow' branching model causes more harm than good. How can we effectively develop and deploy software with confidence?]]></description><link>https://vishalnaik.org/posts/trunk-based-dev-with-deployment-pipelines</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://vishalnaik.org/posts/trunk-based-dev-with-deployment-pipelines</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2015 22:40:32 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;This is my post on ThoughtWorks Insights on &lt;a href=&quot;https://thoughtworks.com/insights/blog/enabling-trunk-based-development-deployment-pipelines&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Enabling Trunk Based Developement With Deployment Pipelines&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Enabling Trunk Based Development with Deployment Pipelines &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/snap_ci?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@snap_ci&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/ContinuousDelivery?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#ContinuousDelivery&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/Bxe4dtuiWD&quot;&gt;https://t.co/Bxe4dtuiWD&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/9MNIiOa2T1&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/9MNIiOa2T1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; ThoughtWorks (@thoughtworks) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/thoughtworks/status/656651115916726272?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;October 21, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Architecture In The Age Of Agile]]></title><description><![CDATA[Does agile software development mean you don't do any upfront architecture?]]></description><link>https://vishalnaik.org/posts/agile-software-design</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://vishalnaik.org/posts/agile-software-design</guid><pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2015 22:40:32 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;One of the things that I try to keep in mind while working on code is &lt;a href=&quot;http://martinfowler.com/bliki/PairProgrammingMisconceptions.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;this quote by Martin Fowler&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I’m writing boring repetitive code it’s usually a sign that I’ve missed an important abstraction, one that will drastically reduce the amount of rote code to write&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Agile, you work in small iterations (week or two weeks at the most) and developers tend to work on work on different parts of the application and diverse features almost every day (pair rotation). So, unless there is a constant reflection of what you are doing, it is easy to miss the forest for the trees, or in our case the important abstractions that can solve a whole class of problems efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of the code level abstractions like say, validation framework or error handling etc. would be naturally implemented while working on code but it can be difficult to identify high level abstractions when you are knee deep into a specific problem and it is much more efficient to identify them ahead of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, for an application that needs to build adapters to various gateways like MQ, FTP, filesystem, email, etc. can we consider integration frameworks like Apache Camel or Spring?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or, if you are building a CRUD interface, is it possible to build a generic solution using a meta-model approach like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.playframework.com/documentation/1.2.3/crud&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, while Agile development eschews big up-front design it is still important to have a high level design in mind with the difference being that in Agile, the plans are not set in stone and can evolve based on changing scope and new learnings.  This &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.infoq.com/news/2010/05/agile-architecture-partnership&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; delves into the inherent tension between agility and upfront planning and design.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Monolith to Microservices]]></title><description><![CDATA[Reflections on a re-architecutre from monolithic app to microservices]]></description><link>https://vishalnaik.org/posts/2015-04-06--monolith-to-microservices/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://vishalnaik.org/posts/2015-04-06--monolith-to-microservices/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 06 Apr 2015 22:40:32 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I was reading Building Microservices recently and couldn’t help but draw parallels to a recent project where we had to work on a monolithic application that ultimately evolved into multiple mini applications that allowed different teams to independently deploy their apps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;single-team-large-codebase&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#single-team-large-codebase&quot; aria-label=&quot;single team large codebase permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Single team, Large codebase&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we started out it was a single large team of atleast 10 dev pairs working off a monolithic code base but different isolated features of the application. While being a single team affords a lot of benefits like easier communication, keeping everybody in sync, better rotation and skill mix, it doesn’t work very well especially for junior members in the team who will find it difficult to focus when they have work on different parts of the application on a continuous basis. This negatively effects code ownership and motivation. I initially didn’t think splitting into smaller teams was a good idea mostly because I thought it would add a lot of communication overhead, hamper cross pollination etc. but now, I think doing so was critical for project delivery, team happiness and code quality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, identifying the seams to divide the teams along, team mix etc. are all important factors to consider before dividing teams. Having the separate teams in the same location, common project showcase meetings and tech huddles should help keep everybody across teams aligned in the larger direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;smaller-teams-separate-codebases&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#smaller-teams-separate-codebases&quot; aria-label=&quot;smaller teams separate codebases permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Smaller teams, separate codebases&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Splitting into smaller teams helped in lot of  ways but every team working on the monolith code base still had some critical problems:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ownership of overall application code was not clear.
Difficult to reason about code in large code bases
Different coding patterns emerged in each team and it was difficult to consolidate
Builds were slow with the large code base, more tests etc.
A broken build would block every team
A large automated functional test suite that was ignored because of lack of ownership&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are typical issues with large monolithic codebases and a side effect of Conway’s Law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Splitting the monolith into smaller independent code bases along functional lines and team structure helped a great deal. We then had a much smaller code base to reason about, much faster builds, test pipelines that were specific to what the team was building and a consistent coding style within the same codebase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;microservices&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#microservices&quot; aria-label=&quot;microservices permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Microservices&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although we had split the codebase along the lines of a team, the deployment of these modules were still as part of the monolithic application. This coupled the release of team specific features with that of the monolith and still retained a significant overhead in deploying software because you need all these different teams to coordinate and sign off on a build and deploy it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While a lot of focus in adoption of CD is lent towards Dev Ops automation, I think having a modular architecture with independently deployable software units is the most important piece because without this you are still stuck with all the  testing and coordination overhead required to deploy the monolith.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dividing the monolithic app into smaller independently deployable mini-apps (fashionably called Microservices) helped address this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teams now have autonomy on releasing software features without being coupled to any other team and have better ownership of their features.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Better Ingredients, Better Software]]></title><description><![CDATA[Fresh perspectives on SW dev from ThoughtWorks]]></description><link>https://vishalnaik.org/posts/better-ingredients-better-software</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://vishalnaik.org/posts/better-ingredients-better-software</guid><pubDate>Sat, 18 May 2013 22:40:32 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Since joining TW (some 18 months now), I have been wanting to write on the key software dev practices that stood out from my previous work places. Here you go:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;relentlessly-automate-every-bit-of-drudgery&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#relentlessly-automate-every-bit-of-drudgery&quot; aria-label=&quot;relentlessly automate every bit of drudgery permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Relentlessly automate every bit of drudgery&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everywhere else I have worked, there is not a lot of attention to be productive at work. It might appear self serving in time and material projects but the real reason is that there is a lack of introspection to see how to build effective software development practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Investments in continuos integration, automated database migration, functional test automation, push button deployment pay off in compound interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;self-organizing-teams-versus-command-and-control&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#self-organizing-teams-versus-command-and-control&quot; aria-label=&quot;self organizing teams versus command and control permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Self Organizing Teams versus Command and Control&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Paul Graham writes, “You weren’t meant to have a boss”.
When everybody in the team know that they can influence a decision, and the best idea will win, everybody feels like they have a stake which is so empowering and motivating. Compare this to a job where the programmer has to simply translate a low level design document and is rewarded for conforming and not asking questions. Inevitably, the measure becomes on terms of Lines of Code or Number of Bugs Fixed per day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stand Ups, Team Retrospectives, Iteration planning meetings, each of these practices have their role in dismantling “command centers” if and when they creep up, even in flat structures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;agile&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#agile&quot; aria-label=&quot;agile permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Agile&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think almost all Waterfall projects that I worked on fell short on one parameter or the other - Quality, Timeliness, Cost, UX. The ones that didn’t, were the ones where we had a very capable client side Product Manager who worked closely with the team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Customer collaboration is the key in ensuring that we deliver the product that the customer wants versus what we think the customer wants. Showcasing to customer frequently and getting feedback, dividing big requirements into smaller “stories”, all these help to stay on track.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, all these things require an all-round, competent, multi-disciplinarian team to make it work and probably works best in smaller teams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;no-broken-windows&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#no-broken-windows&quot; aria-label=&quot;no broken windows permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;No Broken Windows&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have seen a lot of terrible code in the previous IT companies where most projects are won on price factors and this puts a lot of pressure during project delivery because the project cannot afford to bring in experienced developers. New developers starting their careers don’t have much to look up to and the code quality spirals downwards thanks to the Broken Windows Effect. The low margins also mean that the focus is to somehow get the project completed without thinking about code quality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having a maniacal focus on code quality, metrics integrated with CI, pairing, pair rotation etc. helps avoid this pitfall. Therefore, although the early milestones appear to have low velocity but the later releases will certainly be faster and on a strong foundation.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>